# 大家好 家裡的掃把都壞啦
Hi everyone! My broom at home is broken.
# 我們 割點這個芒花 這就個芒花 (註︰標題說是芒草，而這也應該是芒草，芒花應該是他的叫法而已，沒有很好的翻譯，所以不予以配合)
We're gonna get some this kind of silvergrass, I mean the silvergrass here.
# 拿來做一個 做幾個掃把來
We'll make a broom, a couple of brooms using it.
# 這個要帶手套來 不然割手的 安全第一
I gotta wear the gloves. It cuts otherwise. Safety first.
# 你看這個 一割就可以把它割下來
Look! It can be cut down simply with a single pull.
# 農村裡面 就喜歡用這個做掃把
People in the villages love brooms made of silvergrass.
# 老人家 不用錢買啊
I mean the elderlies. It saves money.
# 要把這個一個個敲 敲 敲完來
These need to be all shaken, shaken, shaken off one by one.
# 不敲完的話就
If any of them remains,
# 就沒用 越掃越多
the broom would be useless. If anything, it would only make more dust.
# 這樣 要慢慢的
So it is. It takes time,
# 慢慢的掃
it takes time to clear them all.
# 這個先會回去曬一下 不曬一下搞不了 老是會斷掉
It needs to be dried under the sun at home first. It doesn't work otherwise. It would break very easily.
# 隨便收拾一下
I'm just trying to tidy it up,
# 收拾一下 然後放在家裡面
tidy it up, and then, leave it at home,
# 曬個兩三天 就可以做這個掃把啦
then dry it under the sun for a couple of days. And then we can use it to make brooms.
# 這裡差不多可以做一個
Here's almost enough for a broom.
# 好像還是不夠的
Well, not quite
# 到時候把它紥起來就這樣 咻咻
That's how it looks when we tie it up! Hiup, hiup~!
# 但這個要 把這個毛給搞掉
But we need to, we need to get rid of the fur.
# 這是種子哦
These are the seeds, in fact.
# 撒在哪裡
Where they drop,
# 哪裡就 落地生根
where they, get rooted.
# 還要去割點 不少了 再割點過來
I still need more. It's too little here. Let me cut a bit more.
# 前面好多 你看 一大片都是
There's a lot in the front. It's everywhere.
# 小黑 走 帶你去吃香的喝辣的
Let's go Blacky! I have good food and good drinks for you.
# 哦
Oh?
# 掉啦
It drops.
# 你看
Look!
# 好靚哦 這個
It's really beautiful,
# 看球球的
like a furry ball.
# 你看
Look!
# 就拗了這一點點
So I have just a tiny little bit here.
# 回那個廠裡面去
I'm gonna take it back to, you know, our site.
# 再搞一點 就可以做一個啦
Let me get a bit more. Then it will be enough to make a broom.
# 這個只能做半個
It's only enough for half a broom here.
# 你看 這樣就可以掃地啦
Look! Then we can sweep the floor.
# 掃的很乾淨的哦
It sweeps very well, you know.
# 掃狗
Sweep away the dog
# 它們都胖了
They're getting fat.
# 哎呀 這鴨子就剛剛好
Aya! This duck is perfect.
# 你看 這裡就很多
Look! Here's a lot!
# 從這裡進來
Let's get in from here.
# 你看 這裡就很方便啦
Look! It's really convenient here.
# 雖然搞這個有點麻煩
Though the process is quite a trouble,
# 但是用起來就很方便
the product gives much convenience.
# 你看 現在
Look! Now,
# 這都剛好到那個
right now it's the, I mean,
# 就是 開花的季節 就把它搞掉
like, the blossoming season. And now we cut it off.
# 你看 這種就是沒開花的
Look! These have no flowers.
# 沒開花的也行
But it doesn't matter.
# 這些碎的就把它砍掉
I'm gonna cut off these shattered ones,
# 沒有長的也把它砍掉
and also those which are not growing.
# 砍完之後就到時候 明年它就會長很多出來
After clearing them, later, next year, a lot will be coming out.
# 你看 這個叫芒 芒花
Look! This is called silver, silvergrass.
# 芒草的芒 (註︰這裡就是找一些說了等於沒說的字算了)
Silver, as in silvergrass
# 小花的花
Grass, as in grassland
# 不需要那麼長的 砍短一點
It doesn't need to be that long, cut it short.
# 你看 差不多啦 留點種子給人家
Look! It should be enough now. Gotta leave some here growing.
# 幾棵 幾棵就夠啦
A couple, a couple of them would be enough.
# 不要把它全部砍光啦
Don't cut everything.
# 這些帶回去
Let me take all these back.
# 你看 這個砍回來啦 我要曬幾天
Look! I've taken them all back and gonna dry them under the sun for a few days.
# 就這樣曬著
Just leave them here.
# 過兩天就可以 直接做掃把啦
We can make the brooms using them right away, in a couple of days.
# 今天吃的那個碗都沒收
The bowl that I used today is still here.
# 吃午飯吃的
I used it for my lunch.
# 這個芒杆 曬干了哦
The stems, are all dried now.
# 你看 這個毛 其實就是它的種子來的
Look! The fur, these are the seeds in fact.
# 這個種子
The seeds,
# 要把它
need to be,
# 打 打脫掉
all shake, shaken off.
# 不打脫掉等一下就 越掃越多毛
It simply leaves even more dust if the any of the seeds are left here.
# 你看 現在沒那麼多毛啦
Look! There's much less fur now.
# 這個種子 傳播很快的哦
The seeds, they spread really fast, you know.
# 如果一不小心的話 整個山頭都是這個
The seeds would spread to everywhere in the hill in no time,
# 芒杆的種子 就時候就全部長出這個
if they're not taken care of. And you will see the silvergrass,
# 芒杆啦
everywhere.
# 這個掃把 其實我是不會做的
Frankly speaking, I, I don't really know how to make a broom.
# 剛好攝影小哥的奶奶來啦 叫她幫忙做一下
It just so happens that Mr. Cameraman's grandma is here. I'll ask her to help us.
# 我以前我看過 看過別人做過
I've seen, seen people making them in the past.
# 自己沒做過
But I've never made one myself.
# 叫攝影小哥的奶奶教我做一下
So I'm gonna let Mr. Cameraman's grandma show me how to make one.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 你們在乾甚麼
What are you doing~?
# 我們在紥掃把
We are making brooms~!
# 掃把
Broom!
# 先把這個皮先撕一下 其實這個是 芒杆的葉子
Let me first peel off the skin. It's its leaf, in fact.
# 先把它撕下來 撕下來之後就慢慢地把它紥
I first peel it off, peel it off and then we can spend the rest of the time tying them up.
# 要紥成幾個小捆來做
We need to tie them up in small bunches.
# 我來 幫奶奶打下手
I am here, to be Grandma's assistance.
# 再來一根
One more
# 以前在農村裡面這個掃把都不用買
In the past, we didn't need to buy any brooms in the village.
# 都是自己做 竹葉子都可以做 這個也可以做
Brooms were always made by ourselves. We used bamboo leaves, and silvergrass too.
# 把這個 摘上來一點
This one, make it here.
# 嗯 搞好啦 你看
Um! Done! Have a look!
# 這掃把 很紥實哦
The broom, is really sturdy.
# 搞的很乾淨
It sweeps very well.
# 一塵不染
Completely dustless
# 這裡還有一點點這個
Here's still a little bit of, you know,
# 毛毛 掉完就好啦
the fur. Just let it drop and it's fine.
# 你看 掃這個地 是不是一個小螞蟻都掃的乾乾淨淨
Look! Even a tiny ant, can be swept, swept away from the floor, isn't it?
# 這個掃把 掃的好乾淨的哦這個
This brooms, it really sweeps very well, you know.
# 比買的掃把掃的還乾淨
It's even better then those bought outside.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 你看 就做了一個
Look! One is done now.